<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: culture | Automate All the Things!]]></title>
  <link href="http://dougireton.github.io/blog/categories/culture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dougireton.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-23T21:59:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://dougireton.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Doug Ireton]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Encouraging Women in Dev/Ops]]></title>
    <link href="http://dougireton.github.io/blog/2013/06/23/encouraging-women-in-dev-slash-ops/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-23T21:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://dougireton.github.io/blog/2013/06/23/encouraging-women-in-dev-slash-ops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past week, I went to <a href="http://velocityconf.com/velocity2013">Velocity</a> and <a href="http://devopsdays.org/events/2013-mountainview/program/">DevOps Days</a> in Silicon Valley, CA. Both
conferences were amazing and I learned a ton. During DevOps Days I led an <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/OpenSpace.html">Open
Space</a> session on &ldquo;Encouraging Women in Dev/Ops&rdquo;. I was humbled by the number
of people who attended and their passion for the topic. Read on for a summary of
my notes taken during the hour we had.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li><p>Women will apply for job when they meet 100% of criteria, men 60%
I suspect this is because women are taught not to be boastful as girls, while
boys are taught to &ldquo;go for it&rdquo;. Not sure if there&rsquo;s science to back up this
claim.</p></li>
<li><p>Hiring managers networks contain too few women, so expand those networks.<br/>
Example: Austin has Girls Hack, provides bonding place for women in tech.<br/>
Other cities have women&rsquo;s tech meetups. For example, here&rsquo;s a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/find/?categories=&amp;keywords=women+technology&amp;radius=5">good listing in
Seattle</a></p></li>
<li><p>Benefits: Longer maternity and flex hours are better for women candidates,
job share Foosball table is not necessarily a selling point. Be careful not
to create a &ldquo;dude&rsquo;s&rdquo; environment at work.</p></li>
<li><p>As a manager treat everyone as an individual. Be careful not to treat women
on your team as &ldquo;one of the guys&rdquo;, but also not like a &ldquo;fragile flower&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>We praise women for appearance and kindness; men praised for accomplishments, so
praise women for accomplishments. This is an awareness thing and takes practice.</p></li>
<li><p>&ldquo;Feels great to not be the only woman on team, very empowering&rdquo;. This quote
really struck me. Of course it&rsquo;s better to have one woman on your team than
none, but in order for the woman to not feel like the token woman on the team
it&rsquo;s better to have two or more.</p></li>
<li><p>Need women on DevOps Days Organizaing team. The DevOps Days organizers really
would like women to participate in planning future DevOps Days events. Email
<a href="mailto://info@devopsdays.org">info@devopsdays.org</a> for more information.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
